Spider-Man. The web slinging, friendly, neighbourhood
superhero that we all know and love,
has always been something Marvel Studios wanted to
bring into the Marvel Cinematic Universe, or what we call the MCU.
However, the film rights to Spider-Man belong to Sony Pictures exclusively.
Over the past two decades,
all Spider-Man films have been produced and directed by Sony.
Yet, after the release of The Amazing Spider-Man 2,
the Spider-Man franchise began on a different path.
Through the lens of game theory,
let’s zoom in on how Spider-Man has swung his way from
being a lone superhero saving New York,
to making his entry into the Avengers and
saving the world with other superheroes!
Before diving into his journey,
let’s establish the scope and premise of what we will be talking about today.
Firstly, we assume that the information found online is true,
since most of this information can only be sourced from leaks
instead of official reports.
Next, since merchandising and streaming rights
are independent of film rights,
we will not consider payoffs from merchandising and streaming deals.
Instead, we will solely concentrate on the
payoffs from the movie production deals.
To estimate these payoffs,
we will use the total box office revenue minus the production cost.
With these assumptions in mind,
we will explore three different deals between Marvel and Sony,
updating this timeline as we move along.
For each deal, this is how the game will be played.
Marvel wants to use Sony’s Spider-Man and will first make a business pitch,
after which Sony is able to respond.
If a deal is struck, Marvel will be allowed to use Spider-Man in their films,
and in return, will help produce Spider-Man films for Sony.
But to decide the split between profits of these solo Spider-Man films,
Marvel can make three types of pitches:
The weak 5-95 pitch; the medium 25-75 pitch; or the strong 50-50 pitch.
These represent the splits in profits between
Marvel and Sony respectively.
Sony will then decide whether to accept or reject that offer.
Both players are also allowed to negotiate throughout the process.
Now that we have set things straight, let’s begin the journey!
Going back to where it all started,
after the release of The Amazing Spider-Man 2,
it received tremendous backlash from the audience
due its poor storyline and subpar screenwriting.
Thus, it was expected that the film did poorly in terms of net profits,
and garnered numerous scathing reviews from movie critics and fans alike.
At this stage, let’s revisit our payoff matrix, with the payoffs added in.
To estimate the payoffs of a future Marvel produced Spider-Man movie,
we can use the most recent Marvel superhero movie
released at the time when The Amazing Spider-Man 2 was still out in theatres,
and that would be Captain America: The Winter Soldier.
If Marvel were to propose a weak pitch,
they would get only $27 million in payoffs,
while Sony gets the remaining $517 million.
For a medium pitch, Marvel gets $136 million,
and Sony gets $408 million.
Finally, a strong pitch from Marvel would see profits split equally,
with both parties receiving $272 million.
Meanwhile, on Sony’s side,
they would anticipate their profits for the
next Spider-Man film to be $523 million,
obtained from averaging the payoffs from
the two previous Amazing Spider-Man films.
Marvel initially proposed a weak pitch to Sony.
This is because Marvel knows that if they
were to pitch more aggressively,
Sony will definitely reject them.
The weak pitch was the most viable option
since Sony would be rather indifferent to either option.
Even though the payoffs are similar,
it is evident that Marvel’s deal is much more certain than Sony’s own plans.
Sony’s Spider Man films have been on a
downtrend trend in terms of revenue,
with The Amazing Spider-Man 2 being the lowest ever.
At the same time, Marvel’s superhero films have been performing
exceptionally well in the box office.
Thus, we would expect Sony to go with the
safer option
and accept the weak pitch that Marvel offered.
However, this was not the case.
To explain why Sony rejected Marvel’s deal,
let’s take a look at Sony’s position on the prospect theory curve.
Let’s take The Amazing Spider-Man 1 to be Sony’s initial reference point.
Since The Amazing Spider-Man 2 grossed
lower than The Amazing Spider-Man 1,
this means that Sony is in the loss zone.
From Sony’s perspective, any incremental gain in monetary payoffs
would give them much more utility, making them more risk seeking.
As such, instead of using monetary payoffs in the game matrix,
let’s revisit the matrix in terms of utility.
Recalling the numbers, the additional $6 million
dollars gained
if Sony rejects the deal would be substantial,
now that they are risk-seeking.
In this scenario, even if Sony’s own plans
were more uncertain than Marvel’s offer,
they are unlikely to accept the deal
because of the significant difference in utility.
Thus, they rejected Marvel’s offer and proceeded
on with their own plans.
However, in a dramatic turn of events, Sony’s email servers were hacked,
resulting in a huge email leak.
This leak revealed the negotiations between
Marvel and Sony to the general public,
and exposed the fact that Sony rejected a seemingly favourable deal.
Given that The Amazing Spider-Man 2 was so poorly received,
fans urged Sony to accept Marvel’s offer,
given Marvel’s success with superhero films.
With this, Sony went back to the negotiation table with Marvel.
We now shift our focus to how social pressure
has affected Sony's decision following the leak.
Now, the game matrix changes in Marvel’s favour.
Sony would want to gain the social approval from fans
by accepting Marvel’s offer, because it would give them much more utility.
This additional utility is reflected in the
game matrix
across all pitches, if Sony accepts the deal.
At this point, if they were to choose to produce the films themselves,
the utility would be much lower than if they were to accept Marvel’s offer,
and it would also be much more uncertain.
Given the social pressure,
it is clear that Marvel’s offer is the best choice,
both in terms of utility and certainty.
To prevent any further loss in profits,
and also potentially losing their fans,
Sony gave in to the social pressure
and accepted the deal that Marvel had proposed earlier.
According to this deal, Marvel would be allowed
to use Spider-Man in three of the films:
Captain America: Civil War, Avengers: Infinity War, and Avengers: Endgame.
In return, Marvel will help Sony reboot the
Spider-Man series,
with Spider-Man: Homecoming and Spider-Man: Far from Home.
Marvel will also take 5% of the profits,
with Sony pocketing the remaining 95%.
This time, the films finally broke the downward streak in terms of revenue,
receiving praise from critics and fans around the world
and redeeming the franchise.
After the first deal’s success,
fans were excited for a second deal to see more of Spider-Man in the MCU.
Let us look at our game matrix for deal number 2.
While the previously mentioned movies were
extremely popular,
Sony has also found moderate success in their production of Venom,
a movie independent of the MCU setting.
While Venom is technically related to Spider-Man,
Spider-Man was not involved in this movie.
This makes Venom a good underestimate
of a Sony-produced Spider-Man movie,
(if Sony were to reject Marvel’s deal)
because Spider-Man is generally more
popular than Venom in the box-office.
Conversely, payoffs from the deal are estimated to be
based on profits from Spider-Man: Far From Home,
since that is an estimate of how successful a combined effort can be.
Just from this table,
it seems that Sony is incentivised to continue this partnership,
as long as Marvel sticks with their original
5-95 pitch,
especially after experiencing Spider-Man’s box-office success.
Recognising Spider-Man’s potential,
Marvel proposed to increase their share to a 50/50 split between the studios,
with the possibility of extending the deal to other Spider-Man-related films.
Considering the fairness of the deal,
Marvel’s proposal for a 50-50 split is reasonable,
because their involvement in the Spider-Man films
was a significant reason that heightened the success of Spider-Man,
bearing in mind that Sony’s Spider-Man films suffered harsh reviews
prior to their collaboration with Marvel.
Hence, it seems fair for Marvel to ask for a 50-50 pitch
for attributing the success Spider-Man enjoys at this juncture.
From Sony’s perspective however, this 50-50 split is not fair.
Fairness has to consider the concept of reference
transactions,
which considers the previous deals made.
In this case, given the success of a 5-95
movie deal between Sony and Marvel,
Marvel’s deviation from the 5-95 reference
is perceived  by Sony to be unfair.
Additionally, Sony did not see Marvel as a
deserving recipient of 50% of the profits.
While it is undeniable that Marvel had a significant role
in making Spider-Man great again,
the recent successes that Sony has found in Venom,
and the animated Spider-Man film, “Into The Spider-Verse”,
has made Sony believe that they too, can create good Spider-Man films.
Quoting Tony Vinciquerra, the chairman and CEO of Sony Pictures,
"The Marvel people are terrific people, we have great respect for them,
but on the other hand, we have some pretty terrific people of our own.
[Marvel’s producer] didn't do all the work
we're pretty capable of doing what we have to do here."
While Marvel found the 50-50 split fair,
Sony had a low preference for the 50-50 split
due to its perceived inequality.
As a result, Sony and Marvel were unable to
reach a new movie deal for Spider-Man.
After Far from Home was released,
news revealed that further negotiations between Sony and Marvel broke down,
as both couldn't reach a new agreement regarding Spider-Man films.
This resulted in a more severe fan backlash
because of the inconclusive developments in Spider-Man's storyline.
As of Spider-Man: Far From Home,
the post-credits scene showed the main villain revealing
Spider-Man's secret identity to the entire world,
framing him as a cold-blooded murderer.
If Spider-Man were to leave the MCU,
this major cliffhanger might not be properly resolved,
and fans were extremely upset.
In fact, fans were so upset, that some even threatened
to boycott Sony in retaliation to the news.
Since Sony is also big in the gaming industry with the PlayStation,
fans started the #BoycottSony on Twitter,
asking fellow fans to stop buying the new PS4.
This is likely because fans could not understand why
the two companies could not put aside their differences for the greater good.
Ultimately, the social pressure was so powerful
that the fans drove Spider-Man actor, Tom Holland,
to convince Disney’s CEO, Bob Iger, to renegotiate with Sony,
as seen in this interview.
[Bob Iger] And after D23, Tom reached out to folks who worked for me and said
“Can I please have Bob’s email address or phone number?”.
Of course I am very protected so they were very careful.
And I said “Sure, have him contact me.” And he did, we spoke,
and he basically made a… he cried on the phone.
[Jimmy Kimmel] Did he really?
[Bob Iger] No, not really. (audience laughs)
It was clear that he cared so much and actually we care a lot about him.
He’s a great Spider-Man isn’t he?
[Jimmy Kimmel] He’s the best Spider-Man! (audience cheers)
[Bob Iger] I felt.. I actually... I felt for him
and it was clear the fans wanted all of this to happen.
So after I got off the phone with him,
I made a couple of phone calls to our team at Disney Studios
and then I decided to call the head of Sony.
And I said, “We have to get... We got to figure out a way to get this done,
for Tom and for the fans.”
This incentivised both companies to continue
their collaboration for Spider-Man films.
We have adjusted the payoff matrix to represent
the incentives from the social pressure,
as reflected by an increase in expected utility
for the outcomes where Marvel and Sony successfully make a deal.
The consideration of fairness was critical in helping
Sony and Marvel come to a compromise from their respective pitches.
From the augmented payoff matrix,
we find that the medium 25-75 split helps to increase
Marvel’s payoff from the previous deal,
while also making the outcome attractive to Sony,
since Sony’s perceived payoff for accepting the deal
now outweighs their payoff for refusing it.
Furthermore, the medium 25-75 split
is a nice middle ground between Sony and Marvel’s pitches.
Thus, making it a nice focal point between Sony’s preferred 5-95 split,
and Marvel’s preferred 50-50 split.
In the end, Marvel and Sony agreed to a 25-75
deal,
which would cover 2 more films:
Spider-Man: No Way Home, and a future MCU team-up movie.
Now that we understand how the existing deals came to be,
we want to predict how future Marvel - Sony negotiations will go.
If Sony were to allow Marvel to produce
more Spider-Man movies for them,
potential payoffs can be estimated
by the average of the 3 Spider-Man solo films produced so far.
Similarly, without a deal,
Sony’s payoff can be estimated by the average of their Venom movies.
At first glance, it seems that Sony is likely to accept a deal from Marvel
as long as Sony pockets more than half of the profits.
However, we need to reconsider Sony’s outside options.
Ever since The Amazing Spider-Man franchise,
Sony had plans to expand their universe around Spider-Man,
to compete with the MCU.
In The Amazing Spider-Man 2,
Sony teased the introduction of Spider-Man’s biggest villains,
the Sinister Six.
However, plans were cancelled when The Amazing Spider-Man 2
failed in the box office.
Nevertheless, Sony’s deals with Marvel gave them a second chance,
and Sony successfully produced two Venom films,
indicating the birth of the Sony Spider-Man Universe,
or what we would call the Sony-verse.
Sony’s co-chairman Amy Pascal said in a
report that because of Venom,
Sony’s “previously shelved plans” could now come to fruition.
There have also been reports in 2019,
that the next seven to eight years of the Sony-verse had been planned.
These include movies like Morbius, Kraven the Hunter,
The Sinister Six, Nightwatch, Venom 3 and more.
This becomes a new outside option for Sony
since the potential payoffs from a Sony-verse is very high.
This means that Sony now can still benefit from a large payoff
even without a deal with Marvel.
If Marvel still wishes to use Spider-Man
and help Sony produce movies,
then they would have to give Sony a larger share of the profits
so that Sony would not reject the deal again.
However, this does not seem to be Marvel’s goal,
as demonstrated in the events of the most recently released
Spider-Man: No Way Home.
[Dr. Strange] You’ve got to understand that would mean that everyone
who knows and loves you, we…
we'd have no memory of you.
it would be as though you never existed.
[Spider-Man] I know.
Do it.
This movie essentially becomes a soft reboot for Spider-Man,
because Sony can now utilise him in any way
without affecting the storyline flow in the wider MCU.
This becomes even better news for Sony
because the addition of Spider-Man into the Sony-verse
will only boost the utility that Sony can
get from their outside option.
The soft reboot of Spider-Man also indicates that
the possibility of massive fan backlash is very low.
The social pressure from fans was a key reason
for the success of the first two deals.
In the first deal, fans were upset because
they wanted to see Spider-Man in the MCU
and face off with popular superheroes.
In the second deal, fans were upset because
Spider-Man’s storyline was incomplete
and left on a cliff-hanger that cannot be resolved
if Spider-Man leaves the MCU.
However, as of Spider-Man: No Way Home,
the origin story for Spider-Man has now been satisfactorily concluded.
Additionally, because of how No Way Home leaves
Spider-Man,
he can now be in his own stories without involvement of
major Marvel superheroes like Dr. Strange or Captain America.
Given Sony’s enticing outside option,
and the lack of social pressure from fans,
we predict that another deal of the same kind
between Marvel and Sony is highly unlikely,
and this makes sense.
Sony no longer needs to rely on Marvel’s production team,
or the MCU, to develop Spider-Man’s future stories,
and the fans would still remain satisfied.
However, this does not mean that Spider-Man
would exit the MCU.
In a report, Tom Holland has said that the new agreement
between Sony and Marvel would be that it is an open conversation.
Should Marvel want him to appear in another of their movies,
it would not be the same five-film deal or two-film deal as before.
Therefore, we speculate that if Marvel
wants to use Spider-Man in future films,
they will still approach Sony, but with a deal of a different nature.
Since Marvel no longer has a stake in Spider-Man solo films,
there is no more profit to split between the two companies.
Instead, we think that the new deal
would mainly be an exchange of characters.
In fact, this is what they have been doing.
As explained by Sony Pictures’ chairman, Tom Rothman,
while Sony lends Spider-Man in Marvel movies, Marvel allows characters like
Iron Man and Dr. Strange to appear in Sony’s
(Spider-Man) Homecoming and No Way Home.
Therefore, if Marvel wants to use Spider-Man,
and is willing to lend other characters to Sony,
it is extremely likely that Sony would cooperate and create a new deal.
To recap, we have used various game theory concepts
to explain the deals that revived Spider-Man in movies,
as well as predict the future of Spider-Man in superhero films.
We learnt that there is a common factor among the deals,
and we believe that this is the moral of the story here.
When dealing with film franchises,
we might think that profit is all there is,
and that is partially true.
However, while decision making is based on profit,
it is also strongly influenced by the audience,
because there is a large social pressure from fans all over the world.
Both Marvel and Sony are large companies with power,
and with great power, there must also come great responsibility,
and that responsibility is to us fans.